# Rizqy Amelia Zein

Curriculum Vitae

Assistant Professor

Department of Personality and Social Psychology

Universitas Airlangga

Kampus B UNAIR Jalan Airlangga 4-6 Surabaya

Jawa Timur, Indonesia 60286

Phone: (62) 811-352-0777

Email: amelia.zein@psikologi.unair.ac.id

Web: http://rameliaz.github.io Codes: http://github.com/rameliaz

### Introduction

My PhD project focuses on investigating the relationship between **science-religion** using the lens of **moral cognition theories**. I'm broadly interested in researching **health misinformation**, **conspiracy beliefs**, and **public attitudes to science**. I'm also very passionate about **research methods**, **meta-research**, **computational reproducibility**, **psychometrics**, and **advanced statistical analysis**.

### **Academic Positions**

2018 –	Assistant Professor (Tenured Civil Servant)	Universitas Airlangga
2015 – 2018	Assistant Professor (Probationary Civil Servant)	Universitas Airlangga
2011 – 2015	Temporary Tutor	Universitas Airlangga

### **Education**

2021 –	PhD in Social Psychology (Dr. phil.), Fakultäten für	Ludwig Maxmillian Universität,
	Psychologie und Pädagogik	München, Germany
2012 – 2013	Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Social Research	University of Edinburgh, United
	School of Social and Political Science	Kingdom
2007 – 2011	Sarjana Psikologi (S.Psi.) (GPA: 3.65/4.00)	Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya,
	Faculty of Psychology	Indonesia

## Awards, Honors, and Scholarship

2021	Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst (DAAD), Programm Forschungsstipendien -
	Promotionen in Deutschland
2018	Dean Award of Teaching Excellence
2017	Dean Award of Teaching Excellence
2016	Dean Award of Teaching Excellence
2012	Unggulan Scholarship, Indonesian Ministry of Education and Culture
2011	Awarded cum laude and distinction at undergraduate graduation
2010	Singgih Dirga Gunarsa Award (3 <sup>rd</sup> place)

#### **Grants**

2021	Travel	Attending Aspen Global Congress on Scientific Thinking and Action, The Aspen
		Institute Science and Society Program, Rome, 17-20 March 2021.
2020	Research	Data Collection Grant; Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. International
		Study of Norms Violations during Coronavirus Pandemic, Role: Research

		Collaborator.
2020	Research	42/UN3.1.9/2020; Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. <i>Health Misinformation, Vaccine Hesitancy, and Religiosity: A Meta-Analysis Study.</i> Role: Collaborator.
2019	Travel	Attending Triangle Scholarly Communication Institute (TriangleSCI), Durham (NC), 13-17 October 2019.
2019	Travel	Attending SIPS Pre-Conference RepliCATS workshop, Rotterdam, 6-7 July 2019
2019	Research	Data Collection Grant; Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. <i>International Study of Meta-Norms</i> . Role: Research Collaborator.
2018	Research	886/UN3/2018; Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. <i>Protecting those who care:</i> Comparing subjective and actual risk of contracting lung TB in healthcare workers. Role: PI
2017	Research	39/UN3.1.9/2017; Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga ECR Grant. Do justice and trust matter to supporting social health insurance policy? Role: Pl

### **Scientific Contributions**

### Peer-reviewed journal articles

- Zein, R.A., Wulandari, R.D., Ridlo, I.A., Hendriani, W., Suhariadi, F., & Rianto, A. (2022). The characteristics of occupational Tuberculosis risk in health care workers. *International Journal of Health Planning and Management*. Early view. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/hpm.3489">https://doi.org/10.1002/hpm.3489</a>
- Zein, R. A., Putri, N. K., & Ridlo, I. A. (2020). Do justice and trust affect acceptability of Indonesian social health insurance policy? *International Journal of Health Governance*, 25(1), 78-92. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/IJHG-05-2019-0028">https://doi.org/10.1108/IJHG-05-2019-0028</a>
- 3. **Zein, R. A.** (2018). 'Is Ethnicity the Root of all Evil?' Engaging Macro and Micro Analysis of Ethnic Violence in Post New-order Indonesia. *Politik Indonesia: Indonesian Political Science Review*, 3(2), 262–279. https://doi.org/10.15294/ipsr.v3i2.13985
- 4. **Zein, R. A.**, & Alfian, I. N. (2018). Faktor Determinan Perilaku Konservasi Energi dalam Skala Rumah Tangga dan Sektor Transportasi pada Konsumen Produk Elektronik Ramah Lingkungan dan BBM Non-Subsidi. *Jurnal Psikologi*, 45(3), 231. https://doi.org/10.22146/jpsi.10818
- Zein, R. A. (2018). What's the matter with being Indonesian? A social representation approach to unravelling Indonesian national identity / ¿Qué significa ser indonesio? Una perspectiva de la representación social para desentrañar la identidad nacional indonesia. Revista de Psicologia Social, 33(2), 390–423. https://doi.org/10.1080/02134748.2018.1435219
- 6. **Zein, R. A.**, Suhariadi, F., & Hendriani, W. (2017). Estimating the effect of lay knowledge and prior contact with pulmonary TB patients, on health-belief model in a high-risk pulmonary TB transmission population. *Psychology Research and Behavior Management*, *Volume 10*, 187–194. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S134034">https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S134034</a>

## Collaborations

- Bago, B., [...], Zein, R.A., [...], Hoekstra, R., & Aczel, B. (2022). Situational factors shape moral
  judgements in the trolley dilemma in Eastern, Southern and Western countries in a culturally
  diverse sample. Nature Human Behaviour. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01319-5">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-022-01319-5</a>
- 2. McLamore, Q., [...], **Zein, R.A.**, [...], Yeung, W.L.V., & Burrows, B. (2022). Trust in scientific information mediates associations between conservatism and coronavirus responses in the U.S., but few other nations. *Scientific Reports*, *12*, 3724. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07508-6">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-07508-6</a>

- 3. Eriksson, K., [...], **Zein, R.A.**, [...], Zirganou-Kazolea, L., & Van Lange, P. (2021). Perceptions of the appropriate response to norm violation in 57 societies. *Nature Communication*, *12*(1), 1-11. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21602-9">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21602-9</a>
- 4. Irawan, D. E., Abraham, J., **Zein, R. A.**, Ridlo, I. A., & Aribowo, E. K. (2021). Open access in Indonesia. *Development and Change*, *52*, 651-660. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/dech.12637">https://doi.org/10.1111/dech.12637</a>
- 5. Maison, D., Marchlewska, M., **Zein, R. A.**, Syarifah, D., & Purba, H. (2019). Religiously permissible consumption: The influence of the halal label on product perceptions depending on the centrality of religiosity. *Journal of Islamic Marketing*, *10*(3), 948–960. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/JIMA-07-2018-0119">https://doi.org/10.1108/JIMA-07-2018-0119</a>
- Ridlo, I. A., & Zein, R. A. (2018b). #CondomEmoji: Are urban Indonesians receptive to a social media-based campaign for safer sex? *Health Education*, 118(5), 386–401. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1108/HE-02-2018-0010">https://doi.org/10.1108/HE-02-2018-0010</a>
- 7. Ridlo, I. A., & **Zein, R. A.** (2018a). Arah Kebijakan Kesehatan Mental: Tren Global dan Nasional Serta Tantangan Aktual. *Buletin Penelitian Kesehatan*, *46*(1), 45–52. https://doi.org/10.22435/bpk.v46i1.56
- 8. Maison, D., Marchlewska, M., Syarifah, D., **Zein, R. A.**, & Purba, H. P. (2018). Explicit versus implicit "Halal" information: Influence of the halal label and the country-of-origin information on product perceptions in Indonesia. *Frontiers in Psychology*, *9*(MAR), 1–7. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00382">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00382</a>
- 9. Dewi, T. K., & **Zein, R. A.** (2017). Predicting Intention to Perform Breast Self-Examination: Application of the Theory of Reasoned Action. *Asian Pacific Journal of Cancer Prevention*, 11. <a href="https://doi.org/10.22034/APJCP.2017.18.11.2945">https://doi.org/10.22034/APJCP.2017.18.11.2945</a>
- Fajrianthi, F., & Zein, R. A. (2017). Development of a psychological test to measure ability-based emotional intelligence in the Indonesian workplace using an item response theory. *Psychology Research and Behavior Management, Volume 10*, 339–352. https://doi.org/10.2147/PRBM.S143113
- 11. Suhariadi, F., **Zein, R. A.**, Alfian, I. N., & Hadi, C. (2016). The Tale of Seeking Treatment: A Qualitative Study of Pulmonary Tuberculosis Patients. *Psychology, Community & Health*, *5*(3), 229–243. https://doi.org/10.5964/pch.v5i3.152

### **Book Chapter**

**Zein, R. A.** (2021). Metode Penelitian dalam Psikologi Politik. In W. Yustisia, M. A. Hakim, & R. Ardi (Ed.), *Psikologi politik* (pp. 33-74). Jakarta: Penerbit Buku Kompas.

## **Preprints**

- **Zein, R. A.**, Arinda, M. F., Rikardi, A., Ardelia, V., & Ridlo, I.A. (2020). The enemy of 'ummah: Belief in Jewish conspiracy theories indirectly affected vaccination decisions. *PsyArXiv*. <a href="https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/53qsk">https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/53qsk</a>.
- **Zein, R. A.,** Gollwitzer, M., & Dharmaputra, R. (2022). "It all boils down to Jews" Antisemitic conspiracy beliefs predict Indonesians' endorsement for pro-Russian sentiments on the Ukraine war. *Submitted to Social Psychology.*

### Selected non-peer-reviewed writings & op-eds

1. **Zein, R.A.** (2021). Open science can help accelerate – and protect – high-quality research in

- low-income countries. The Conversation France.
- 2. **Zein, R.A.** (2021). 27% penduduk Indonesia masih ragu terhadap vaksin COVID-19, mengapa penting meyakinkan mereka. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 3. **Zein, R.A.** (2020). Mengapa anjuran "berpikir positif" saat pandemi COVID-19 justru bahayakan nyawa banyak orang. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 4. Irawan, D.E., Abraham, J., **Zein, R.A.**, & Gutham, S. (2020). India's plan to pay journal subscription fees for all its citizen may end up making science harder to access. *The Conversation Indonesia*.
- 5. **Zein, R. A.** (2019). Prabowo Tak Percaya Hasil Hitung Cepat: Mengapa partisan berpikir konspiratif? *The Conversation Indonesia*.

## Collaborative multi-national projects

- 1. 2022 University of Michigan, United States (US). *Cross-Cultural Disgust Perception Project.* PI: Joshua Ackerman, Daniel M. T. Fessler, & Thomas Kupfer.
- 2. 2021 University of Sussex, United Kingdom (UK). *The convergent and discriminant validity of maths anxiety and statistics anxiety: A multi-site, multi-study project.* PI: Prof. Andy Field and Jenny Terry (University of Sussex, Brighton, UK).
- 3. 2020 Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. *International Study of Norms Violations during Coronavirus Pandemic*. Pl: Dr. Giulia Andrighetto (Institute of Cognitive Sciences and Technology, Italy).
- 2020 Psychological Science Accelerator (PSA). Moral thinking across the world: Exploring the influence of personal force and intention in moral dilemma judgements. [Accepted 1st stage registered report in Nature Human Behavior). Pl: Dr. Balasz Aczel (ELTE University, Hungary).
- University of Massachusetts, Amherst. The persuasiveness of strategic science communication on compliance with scientific recommendations across Nations during the COVID-19 pandemic. PI: Dr. Bernhard Leidner (UMass, Amherst).
- 6. 2019 Institute for Future Studies (IFFS) Sweden. *International Study of Meta-Norms.* PI: Dr. Kimmo Eriksson (University of Stockholm).

### **Professional Community Services**

### Ad-hoc peer-review

Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies (x2), PLoS ONE (x6), Social Justice Research (1x), Psychology and Sexuality (x1), Psychology Research and Behavior Management (x1), Jurnal Berkala Epidemiologi (x1), MAKARA Human Behavior Studies in Asia (x1), Journal of Social Psychology (x3), International Quarterly of Community Health Education (1x).

#### **Others**

2021-present	Volunteer, PhDMamaIndonesia
2019	Committee, 36th Anniversary of Faculty of Psychology
2019	Committee, Webinar Sains – Advancing Science in Indonesia: Current Global Research
	Practices
2019-present	Member/Co-Founder, Sains Terbuka Airlangga (https://sainsterbukaua.github.io/)
2019-present	Researcher-in-training, Institute for Globally Distributed Open Research and Education
	(IGDORE)

2019-2020 **Volunteer**, INArxiv pre-print server

2016-present Editor-in-chief, INSAN Jurnal Psikologi dan Kesehatan Mental

# **Presentations**

## **Invited talks**

14/09/2022	Internasionalisasi, Pemeringkatan, dan Integritas Akademik di Universitas, Fakultas
	Keguruan dan Ilmu Pendidikan (FKIP) Universitas Muhammadiyah Prof. Dr. HAMKA
27/08/2020	Mengelola Pembelajaran Jarak-Jauh dengan Online Delivery, Fakultas Psikologi Universitas
	Airlangga
08/08/2020	Penolakan Vaksin, Kepercayaan Konspiratif, dan Bagaimana Menyikapinya, Webinar Series:
	Ilmuwan Merespon Pandemi, Society of Indonesian Science Journalists (SISJ) & Akademi
	Ilmuwan Muda Indonesia (ALMI)
05/04/2020	Sintesis Pengetahuan dengan Meninjau Literatur, Department of Health Policy and
	Administration Universitas Airlangga
21/09/2019	Menulis Artikel Opini dan Komunikasi Sains, Kelas Literasi Klub Seri Buku
08/08/2019	Menulis Artikel Populer dari Karya Ilmiah, Direktorat Sistem Informasi (DSI) Universitas
	Airlangga
07/23/2019	Self-Archiving, The Conversation Indonesia Writing Workshop
19/07/2019	Self-Archiving and Introduction to Open Science, The Indonesian Journal of Health
	Administration Workshop
25/04/2019	Encouraging Academics to Embrace #OpenScience, The 5th UGM Public Health Symposium
21/01/2019	Challenging Religious Extremism: Social Psychology Perspective, Universitas Nahdlatul
	'Ulama Surabaya

# Workshops

30/01/2020	Confirmatory Factor Analysis, Faculty of Education Universitas Negeri Semarang
22-23/11/2019	Multigroup Structural Equation Modeling, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga
02/11/2019	Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Islam Sultan
	Agung, Semarang
04/09/2019	Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga
05/10/2018	Statistical Power Workshop, Faculty of Psychology Universitas Airlangga

# **Professional Development**

# Workshops

18/08/2020	Good Clinical Practice, NDA Clinical Trials Network
01/11/2018	Multilevel Modeling, Indonesian Association of Social Psychology (IPS)
14/12/2017	Psychological Test Adaptation, HIMPSI Jawa Timur
20/11/2017	Basic and Advanced Training on Bioethics, Faculty of Public Health Universitas
	Airlangga
10-21/04/2017	Applied Approach, Universitas Airlangga
06-10/03/2017	PEKERTI, Universitas Airlangga
24/07 - 6/12/2017	Pelatihan Dasar Calon PNS Golongan III, Pusdiklat Kementerian Pendidikan dan
	Kebudayaan

### **MOOCs**

23/10/2019	Improving your statistical questions, TU Eindhoven, Coursera
01/02/2019	Improving your statistical inferences, TU Eindhoven, Coursera
03/04/2018	Inferential statistics, University of Amsterdam, Coursera

#### **Summer School**

07/03/2013 Advanced Issues in Survey Design and Analysis, Utrecht University

### **Professional Membership**

2020-present	Society of Indonesian Science Journalists (SISJ)
2019-present	Society for the Improvement of Psychological Sciences (SIPS)
2017-present	Asian Association of Social Psychology (AASP)
2017-present	International Society of Political Psychology (ISPP)
2013-present	Indonesian Association of Social Psychology (IPS)

### **Skills**

## Language

Native	Bahasa Jawa
Native	Bahasa Indonesia
C1	English, IELTS 7.5 (2020, Listening 8.0, Reading 8.5, Writing 6.5, & Speaking 7.5)
A2	German
A1	Japanese

## Methodology/Statistics

Lab.js
Latent Response Model
Directed Acyclic Graphs (DAG)
Network Analysis
Systematic Review
Meta-Analysis
Multilevel Modeling/Linear Mixed Effect
Latent Variable Modeling
General Linear Models
Generalised Linear Models
Sosci Survey, SurveyMonkey, LimeSurvey, Qualtrics, & formr

## **Programming**

HTML PHP R

## Mentorship

2021 **Riezky Putra Santoso,** undergraduate thesis

2021	Faza Izzudin Nuha, undergraduate thesis
2021	Fiona Fira Winata, undergraduate thesis
2020	Naufal A. Farisy, undergraduate thesis
2020	Sita Nadia Salsabilla Widodo, undergraduate thesis
2020	Hibatullah Anfal Farisi, undergraduate thesis
2020	Maghfira Fahmi Arinda, undergraduate thesis
2020	Audi Ahmad Rikardi, undergraduate thesis

### **Teaching**

**Odd Semester** PSK301 Community Mental Health

2020/2021 PSA212 Community Assessment and Intervention

PSU108 Personality Psychology (Regular Programme)

PSU108 Personality Psychology (IUP/AMERTA)

PHP101 Philosophy of Science (IUP) PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

**Even Semester** PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods and Data Analysis

PSS104 Social Cognition (Regular Programme) 2020/2021

> PSS104 Social Cognition (IUP/AMERTA) PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods (Master of Professional Psychology)

MAS702 Advanced Statistics (Master of Professional Psychology)

PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

**Odd Semester** PHP102 Human Philosophy

2019/2020 PSU108 Personality Psychology (Regular Programme)

PSU108 Personality Psychology (IUP/AMERTA)

PSK301 Community Mental Health PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

**Even Semester** PSS104 Social Cognition (Regular Programme) 2019/2020 PSS104 Social Cognition (IUP/AMERTA)

PSU104 History and System of Psychology

**PSS105 Social Interactions** 

PSS405 Social Psychology Seminar

PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods (Master of Professional Psychology)

MAS702 Advanced Statistics (Master of Professional Psychology)

**Odd Semester** PHP102 Human Philosophy (IUP)

2018/2019 PHP102 Human Philosophy (Regular Programme)

PHP101 Philosophy of Science (Regular Programme)

PHP101 Philosophy of Science (IUP) PSU108 Personality Psychology (IUP) PSK301 Community Mental Health

PNP206 Quantitative Research Methods and Data Analysis

**Even Semester** PSS104 Social Cognition (Regular Programme)

2018/2019 PSS104 Social Cognition (IUP)

PSU104 History and System of Psychology

**PSS105 Social Interactions** 

MAS702 Advanced Statistics (Master of Professional Psychology)